Finding Aid for Michigan Manufacturers Association records, 1902-1997
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Manufacturers Association records 1902-1997
Michigan Manufacturer's Association.
20 linear feet
0786 Bc 2
Organization established in 1902 to represent the interests of industrial manufacturers in dealings with state government; publications, administrative records, correspondence, topical files, photographs, and other materials detailing the work of the organization.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was donated by the Michigan Manufacturers Association (donor no. 9889 ) in May 2007.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The record group is open to research.
Established in 1902, the Michigan Manufacturers Association brought together a group of manufacturers who had separately come to Lansing to testify on behalf of legislation affecting the growth of their businesses. With then no organization to represent their interests, these individuals saw the need to have a single voice when speaking to the different branches of state government. The MMA, from its original membership of 130, flourished and grew, expanding and adapting its programs to coincide with the changing needs of Michigan's manufacturing firms. In 1992, the membership numbered 2700, nearly 90% of the state's industrial employers.
In 1908, the MMA organized employers to establish a system for compensating injured workers. In 1912, based on a proposal authored by the MMA, Michigan's first Workers Compensation Act became law. During the depression, the MMA worked with state and industry officials on passing an unemployment compensation act. And in 1943, the MMA became the first such association in the nation to offer a group insurance program to its members. More recently, the organization has lobbied on behalf of what it believed would be a more equitable system of taxation, one would spur economic growth.
In its role as a watchdog of legislation pending before Congress and before the state legislature, the MMA has published for its members a variety of newsletters and digests. One of these was Legislative Digest (checklist of bills introduced in the Michigan House and Senate); another was Letter from Lansing (a report on issues being considered in Lansing).
The records of the Michigan Manufacturers Association have been arranged into the following series: Administrative records; Bulletins; Print masters of Enterprise and other mailings; Collected historical materials; Photographs; John C. McCurry (General Manager; John G. Thodis (Director of Government Relations and later President); and Topical files: George M. Van Peursem and John G. Thodis.
Subjects:
Michigan Manufacturer's Association.; Manufactures--Michigan.; Manufacturing industries--Michigan.; Michigan--Economic conditions.; Manufacturing industries--Government policy--Michigan.
Contributors:
Lovett, John L.; McCurry, John C.; Thodis, John G.; Van Peursem, George M.
- Administrative records
  - Reports of annual meetings 1915-1982, 1 folders (Box 1)
    (many gaps; record set of reports remain with donor)
  - Minutes of board of trustees 1917-1984, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (many gaps; record set of minutes remain with donor)
- Bulletins
  (the earlier volumes include some correspondence; up to 1921 the volumes include transcripts of speeches from the annual meetings)
  - May 1908-December 1910, 1 volumes (Box 1)
  - January 1911-February 1913, 1 volumes (Box 1)
  - 1916-1918, 1 volumes (Box 1)
  - 1919, 1 volumes (Box 1)
  - 1920, 1 volumes (Box 1)
  - 1921 (Box 1)
    (the records from 1921 to 1989 were microfilmed by the organization which retained the film)
  - 1922 (Box 1)
  - 1923 (Box 1)
  - 1924-1927 (Box 2)
  - 1928-1930 (Box 2)
  - 1931-1934 (Box 2)
  - 1934-1937 (Box 2)
  - 1938-1940 (Box 2)
  - 1940-1943 (Box 2)
  - 1943-1945 (Box 2)
  - 1946-1948 (Box 2)
    (most issues missing)
  - 1948-1950 (Box 2)
  - 1950-1951 (Box 2)
  - 1951 (Box 2)
  - 1951-1952 (Box 2)
  - 1953-1954 (Letter from Lansing and Legislative Digest) (Box 2)
  - 1952-1954 (bulletins) (Box 2)
  - 1953-1954 (bulletins and mailings) (Box 2)
  - 1955-1959 (Box 3)
  - 1960-1968 (Box 4)
  - 1969-1976 (Box 5)
  - 1977-1981 (Box 6)
  - 1982-1989 (Box 7)
- Print masters of Enterprise and other mailings
  (this series seems to continue the Bulletins series)
  - 1989-1990 (Box 8)
  - 1990 (Box 9)
  - 1991 (Box 10)
  - 1991 (Box 11)
  - 1992 (Box 12)
  - 1992 (Box 13)
  - 1993 (Box 14)
  - 1993 (Box 15)
- Collected historical materials
  - Dated materials
    (the early files are mainly directories and other published material; after 1917 the files consist of correspondence, proposed legislative bills, and memoranda taken from the office of the Secretary, General Manager and General Counsel of the MMA)
    - 1902-1916 (Box 16)
    - 1917 (Box 16)
    - 1918 (Box 16)
      (include correspondence and other papers of J. G. Hoffmann, MMA secretary)
    - 1919, 2 folders (Box 16)
      (include correspondence of Hoffman and General Manager John L. Lovett relating to pending legislation of interest to the organization)
    - 1920 (Box 16)
    - 1921 (Box 16)
      (include correspondence of General Manager and General Counsel Hal Smith)
    - 1922 (Box 16)
      (correspondence of General Counsel Hal Smith)
    - 1923 (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Membership dues book circa 1910-1918 (Box 16)
    - Notebook in containing list of membership one part arranged by trade and one part arranged by city, 2 volumes (Box 16)
    - Legislation (various) undated (Box 17)
    - John L. Lovett, General Manager
      - Clippings of column "Under the Dome at Lansing" 1927-1931 (Box 17)
      - General clippings about the economy or world affairs 1931 (Box 17)
- Photographs
  - Portraits of Michigan legislators, members of Congress, governors, and other Michigan public figures (Box 17)
  - "Let's Talk It Over" slide presentation (Box 17)
  - Unidentified slide presentation (Box 17)
- John C. McCurry (General Manager)
  - Correspondence 1952 (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous 1953-1960 (Box 18)
  - Speeches (Box 18)
- John G. Thodis (Director of Government Relations and later President)
  - Correspondence with Michigan legislators 1981-1985 (Box 18)
  - Correspondence with Governor William Milliken 1973-1982 (Box 18)
  - Re Governor Milliken's "Economic Recovery Package" 1981-1982 (Box 18)
  - Michigan Dept. of Labor 1972-1981 (Box 18)
  - Michigan Dept. of Commerce 1973-1981 (Box 18)
  - Correspondence with MMA board members
    - Caldwell, Bob (Box 18)
    - Derleth, Robert J. (Box 18)
    - Kowalski, Steve (Box 18)
    - Lomason, W.K. (Box 18)
    - McNaughton, Chris (Box 18)
    - Magill, Bob (Box 18)
    - Pingel, John S. (Box 18)
    - Poxson, Elijah (Box 18)
    - Wallace, John J. (Box 18)
  - Career materials: binders containing correspondence, speeches, clippings regarding government service, and papers written, 2 volumes (Box 18)
  - Clippings 1979 (Box 18)
  - Career recognition in professional publications 1997 (Box 18)
- Topical files: George M. Van Peursem and John G. Thodis
  - Albion College appearance March 12, 1985 (Box 19)
  - Arthur Andersen -- joint survey with MMA regarding competitiveness of auto industry and its parts suppliers 1979-1983 (Box 19)
  - Auto Supplier Action Council (Box 19)
  - Automobile industry (general) (Box 19)
  - Blanchard, James G. (Governor) (Box 19)
  - Business climate in Michigan, etc. (Box 19)
  - "Businessman's Responsibility in Politics" speech given September 16, 1958 (Box 19)
  - Buy Right program 1987-1988 (Box 19)
  - China -- Michigan and China Committee 1983-1985 (Box 19)
  - Chiropractic bill 1992 (Box 19)
  - City Club of Lansing 1989 (Box 19)
  - Conference of State Manufacturers Association (COSMA) 1963-1981 (scattered dates) (Box 19)
  - Economic climate survey 1956 (Box 19)
  - Education Reform Agenda (brochure) (Box 19)
  - Golf Outings (Box 19)
  - Governmental re-organization 1965 (Box 19)
  - Governor's Task Force on Access to Health Care 1990 (Box 19)
  - History and anniversary celebrations
    - General (Box 19)
    - 75th anniversary 1977 (Box 19)
    - 80th anniversary 1982 (Box 19)
    - 90th anniversary 1992 (Box 19)
  - Legislative apportionment in Michigan 1991 (Box 19)
  - Litigation
    - Caterpillar v Michigan Dept. of Treasury 1991 (Box 19)
    - Trinova Corp. v. Michigan Dept. of Treasury 1990-1991 (Box 19)
  - Michigan Manufacturers Association
    - Bicentennial Project (Box 19)
    - Board of Directors Legislative Update 1991-1992, 4 folders (Box 19)
    - Board of Directors meeting January 1991 (Box 19)
    - Board of Directors meeting June 27, 1991 (Box 19)
      (regarding legislative agenda 1991-1992)
    - Projects Committee (Box 20)
    - Reorganization and other news of the organization (Box 20)
    - Sales and Exchange Bulletin 1974 (Box 20)
    - Tax Advisory Committee (Box 20)
    - "What is MMA" (booklet) (Box 20)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 20)
  - Project NorthStar (Box 20)
  - Proposal A & B 1988-1990 (raising taxes for school education) (Box 20)
  - Proposal C (shifting decision-making on tax matters from the legislature to the electorate) (Box 20)
  - Regulatory reform 1981 (Box 20)
  - Revitalization of Michigan Industry 1981 (Box 20)
  - Romney, Governor George -- miscellaneous (Box 20)
  - Seminars (various) (Box 20)
  - Unemployment compensation legislation ("honorable compromise") 1975-1976 (Box 20)
  - Williams, Governor G. Mennen -- "anti-business" bills circa 1956 (Box 20)
  - Workmen's Compensation Reform Task Force 1979 (Box 20)